<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Horologiographia nocturna. Or Lunar horologiographie Set forth and demonstrated (after a twofold manner) in the horizontall plane onely. Vpon which (and all other by the same reason) may in a manner, as plainely and speedily bee discerned the times of the night by the gnomonicall shadow, caused by the moone, as the times of the day upon any by the sun: serving as well in the day time for the sunne. By Iohn Wyberd. Together with an addition of certaine new and briefe rules for the exact and most speedy mensuration of circles and spheres, and also cylinders, both in solid and liquid measure, by certaine plaine scales onely, not heretofore published, but now set forth for the benefit of all those that have occasion to make use of such things.</title>
            <author>Wybard, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120439</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 946:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Horologiographia nocturna. Or Lunar horologiographie Set forth and demonstrated (after a twofold manner) in the horizontall plane onely. Vpon which (and all other by the same reason) may in a manner, as plainely and speedily bee discerned the times of the night by the gnomonicall shadow, caused by the moone, as the times of the day upon any by the sun: serving as well in the day time for the sunne. By Iohn Wyberd. Together with an addition of certaine new and briefe rules for the exact and most speedy mensuration of circles and spheres, and also cylinders, both in solid and liquid measure, by certaine plaine scales onely, not heretofore published, but now set forth for the benefit of all those that have occasion to make use of such things.</title>
                  <author>Wybard, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p., [3] folded plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Cotes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The "plates" are woodcuts.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21137:1"/>
            <p>HOROLOGIOGRAPHIA NOCTVRNA.</p>
            <p>OR <hi>LVNAR HOROLOGIOGRAPHIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set forth and demonſtrated (after a twofold manner) in the Horizontall Plane onely.</p>
            <p>Vpon which (and all other by the ſame reaſon) may in a manner, as plainely and ſpeedily bee diſcerned the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes of the Night by the Gnomonicall ſhadow, cauſed by the Moone, as the times of the Day upon any by the Sun: Serving as well in the day time for the Sunne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN WYBERD.</p>
            <p>Together with an Addition of certaine new and briefe Rules for the exact and moſt ſpeedy menſuration of Circles and Spheres, and alſo Cylinders, both in ſolid and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid meaſure, by certaine plaine Scales onely, not hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore publiſhed, but now ſet forth for the benefit of all thoſe that have occaſion to make uſe of ſuch things.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Eſt natura hominum novitatis avida.</q> 
               <bibl>Plin.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Cotes.</hi> 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21137:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21137:2"/>
            <head>A DESCRIPTION OF THE HORIZONTALL <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NAR DYALL.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <head>Place this Figure next after page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>The houres in every Circle, are continued on both ſides of the Meridian line, ſo farre as the houre-lines for the Sunne doe extend, that ſo the Dyall might ſerve generally for all times of the yeare; and though the houre of 12. falleth twice in ſome of them, yet may they both be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at one time of the yeare or other; for to place in ſuch houres onely as ſhall happen to be of uſe, and neither more nor leſſe, is a thing I conceive not to bee certainely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21137:13"/> done by reaſon of the uncertaine riſing and ſetting of the Moone, and her uncertaine departure from the rayes of the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Having noted downe the houres in every circle (as in the ſecond figure) adde to each circle one or two inward circles, making one or two convenient ſpaces for the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in of little lines or ſtrokes, for the houres and their parts (according to the uſuall manner) and the figures belonging to them: but in the latter way you muſt adde to each circle, three other inward circles, making three ſeverall ſpaces for the three rankes of figures belonging to every circle, (as you may ſee in the third and laſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure) becauſe the houre-lines of every circle (as I ſayd before) be here of a threefold denomination: and it is neceſſary for you ſo to order and contrive the circles on your plane, as that there may be left a convenient ſpace betweene every ſeverall Dyall or circle of houres, to diſtinguiſh betweene them, and not to mingle and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them one with another.</p>
            <p>The parts of every houre neceſſary to be placed on the Dyall (though we have put none here, partly to avoyd tediouſneſſe in the worke, and ſome charge in cutting the figures, and partly becauſe the are needeleſſe in this place) may be thoſe which we have formerly uſed, or better it were for common uſe to have each houre divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſome equall number of parts, as foure or eight parts, as is uſually done in moſt Sun-dyals; for before we divided each houre into five parts, as being the fitteſt number for the more eaſie and exact making of the Dyall.</p>
            <p>The outermoſt circle of all, belonging to the fifteenth day of the Moone or day of oppoſition, ſerveth aſwell for the Sunne, the houre-lines thereof being rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the Sunne. For the Moone, on the day of her coujunction with the Sunne, commeth to the Meridian much about the time that he doth, and in the day of her
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21137:13"/> oppoſition to the Sunne, ſhe commeth to the ſayd place at the oppoſite time or thereabout, when the Sunne is in the North point of the Meridian circle, under the ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or our Horizon, that is, at our Mid-night or 12. of the clocke (as the former Table ſheweth) and then the ſame Dyall which ſerveth to ſhew the houre of the day by the Sunne, ſerveth likewiſe to ſhew the houre of the night by the Moone, though not alwayes ſo exactly, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difference to be regarded in common uſe (as I have oftentimes obſerved) but at other times it cannot be ſo, becauſe the time of the Moones aforeſayd mediation or culmination, is not alwayes the ſame, but altereth on every day, and therefore that Dyall which ſhould ſerve to ſhew the houres or times of any other night by the Moone, muſt (of neceſſitie) be altered, and the houte-lines bee otherwiſe ordered and diſpoſed, or elſe why ſhould not the Moone in any night when ſhe ſhineth, ſhew the true houres thereof upon any true Sunne-Dyall by the ſtilar ſhadow, aſwell as the Sunne ſheweth the true houres of any day by the ſame; which thing, how farre it is from being ſo, I thinke there is ſcarcely no ordinary man that doth not know it; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof being (as I ſhewed before) becauſe the Moone doth not alwayes obſerve the ſame times with the Sunne, in her riſing, Southing, and ſetting.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſeverall Dyals or circles of houres, may not onely be delineated upon the Horizontall Plane, to ſhew the time of the night by the Moone, but alſo upon all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther planes by the ſame reaſon and rule, (and therefore we have here entitled it, <hi>Lunar Horologiographie,</hi> that is, <hi>The Deſcription of Dyals for the Moone</hi>) and moſt readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Equinoctiall Plane, by reaſon of the equality of the horariall angles: And in the direct Meridian and Polar Planes, where the <hi>Solar</hi> houre-lines are parallels, there alſo the <hi>Lunar</hi> will be parallels; and in ſtead of thoſe fifteene concentricall circles formerly uſed, here muſt bee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21137:14"/> fifteene parallell right lines, of which the equinoctiall line of the Plane, may very fitly be one, which may (if you pleaſe) ſerve for the fifteenth day of the Moone, and ſo will ſerve continually for the Sunne by the reaſon aforeſayd: So the ſeven Parallels falling under the ſayd line, may then fitly ſerve for the ſeven dayes next enfuing the day of her change and Full, and the ſeven Paralells above the ſayd line, for the ſeven dayes next before the Full, and the change next following: or you may begin at the uppermoſt parallell on the Plane, and account that for one day and ſixteene dayes of the Moone, and ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downewards, the loweſt parallell will be for fifteene and thirty dayes, and ſo for the Sunne, and then the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall line or middle parallell ſhall be for eight and 23. dayes, for you may begin with what parallell you will: then drawing the common houre-lines of theſe Planes, and dividing each hour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into five parts (as before) the houres for the Moone are ſet off from the houre-lines of 6. in the one and 12. in the other on both ſides thereof upon their proper parallels, (as farre as the houre-lines for the Sunne doe extend) with as much facility as in any other Plane whatſoever, the Equinoctiall plane being excepted; ſo that you bee carefull to place the right houres in theſe planes: Having thus ſet downe the houres (and parts if you pleaſe) draw to each Parallell line another parallell including a convenient ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, wherein to draw little lines or ſtrokes for the houres and their parts, and to place the figures belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the houre-lines or ſtrokes: But for that I ſhewed before, how this might bee performed by five circles in the Horizontall plane, ſo by the ſame reaſon it may here be performed by five parallells onely, for then each pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell ſerveth for ſixe dayes, and the houre-lines of each parallell are of a threefold denomination, and then you muſt draw to each parallell line, three other parallels, that ſo there may be three fitting ſpaces made for the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21137:14"/> of three rowes of figures which belong to the houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of every parallell, as was done by circles in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontall plane; and in the delineating of any of theſe Dyalls, it were convenient for you firſt to draw the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (or Solar) houre-lines belonging to the plane, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely with the point of your compaſſe or ſuch like thing upon your plane, by which you may eaſily diſcerne whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you worke rightly or not: But to deliver any figure here concerning theſe laſt mentioned planes I thinke it to be needeleſſe, becauſe if the working upon the former be rightly underſtood, the working upon theſe latter and likewiſe upon all other Planes may eaſily be underſtood by the ſame reaſon: And as for the ſtile belonging to to theſe laſt named Planes, it is neceſſary that the ſame be made full as broad as the Plane of the houre-lines, (or if it were a little broader in the top, it were not amiſſe) that ſo the ſhadow thereof may alwayes extend as farre as the parallell lines on the Plane; for though a ſtraight round pin will ſerve in theſe Planes for a ſtile for the Sunne, yet it will not for the Moone, by reaſon of the varietie of Dyals on one and the ſelfe ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Plane, all differing one from another: But indeed none other is ſo commodious for common uſe as the Horizontall Dyall, which may (moſt eaſily) be fitted for uſe two manner of wayes: For it may be either alwayes fixed abroad, like unto the common horizontall Sun-Dyall, and ſo be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, or elſe not fixed, but to be removed up and downe at pleaſure, and then having a Magneticall Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle placed in a Boxe after the uſuall manner (whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian line ought to be drawne therein, according to the deflection or variation of the Needle in the place of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation) to be affixed to ſome ſide thereof, it may bee truely placed thereby, any night when it ſhould be uſed, being holden or ſet preciſely horizontall; or (for want of ſuch a Needle) they that have an horizontall Sunne-Dyall about their houſe truely placed, may make a ſhift to uſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21137:15"/> it well enough, by laying it flat upon that Dyall, and then applying one ſide the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eof to the ſide of the cocke or ftile of that Dyall, in ſuch ſort that the Meridian line of the one may be paralell to the Meridian line of the other. But indeed the moſt abſolute way of all, were to have it made in braſſe (which may be done by Mr. <hi>Elias Allen</hi> dwelling without <hi>Temple</hi> Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, over againſt St. <hi>Clements</hi> Church, <hi>London,</hi> who maketh all ſorts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mathematicall Inſtruments and alſo horizontall Sunne-Dyalls in braſſe) and fixed alwayes upon a poaſt, or rather made upon a faire white ſtone, where the ſtrokes for the houres and their parts and the figures belonging to them being done in blacke or other ſuch notable colour, might be more perfectly diſcerned than in the other: So that then onely knowing the day of the Moone, (which may be knowne by any Almanacke) you have no more to doe, (the Moone ſhining on the Plane) but to looke out the circle which is appropriated to that day, and the ſhadow of the ſtile will preſently give you the houre or time of the night, if your Dyall be rightly made and placed: And it would be very comely and convenient to have the ſtile to this Dyall made ſo, as it ſhould touch the plane in thoſe places onely where it is let into the ſame, that is, betweene the center and the circle next unto it, and againe a little about the outermoſt circle which is furtheſt from the center, that ſo the ſtroakes for the houres and their parts, and the figures which fall upon or very neere the Meridian line, might not be hidden and defaced by the ſtile.</p>
            <p>But becauſe houre-lines may be placed generally upon all planes (as I ſayd before) to ſhew the houres of the night by the Moone; it would be an excellent way to have a Lunar Dyall drawne on glaſſe and placed in a window after the manner of thoſe Sunne-Dyalls which are moſt accurately made by my loving friend Mr. <hi>Baptiſt Sutton,</hi> dwelling at the upper end of <hi>Chauncery</hi> Lane, neere <hi>Holborne</hi> (being the author of the enſuing worke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21137:15"/> or Addition) who likewiſe will be able to performe theſe as accurately as the other, if it ſhall be required of him: For there the plane of the Dyall being of a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent matter, and intercepted (as a meane object) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the eye and the Moone, the houre-ſtroakes and figures, together with the ſhadow of the ſtile, may bee thereupon more perfectly and ſpeedily diſcerned, than upon any other kinde of Plane whatſoever (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought it not amiſſe to give notice thereof) but it is well knowne that the ſhadow which is cauſed by the Moone, cannot be altogether ſo perfectly diſcerned as that which is cauſed by the Sunne, becauſe the light of the Moone is not ſo perfect as the light of the Sunne, and therefore the time of the day may be ſomewhat more readily perceived on the Dyall by the ſtilar ſhadow, than the time of the night; yet it may be very eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned thereby, eſpecially when the Moone ſhineth out very bright.</p>
            <p>And now, this our Horizontall Dyall I conceive (and I thinke, that any man of underſtanding will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to be farre more eaſie and ready in uſe, than that Lunar Dyall which Mr. <hi>Fale</hi> hath long agoe deſcribed, in his booke of <hi>Solar Horologiographie,</hi> whoſe poſition muſt be in direct Paralelliſme to the Equinoctiall circle of the Sphere, making the ſame angle (of inclination) with the Plane of the Horizon, which that doth, being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the Latitude or Polar altitude, and therefore but few men know how to make uſe thereof in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of them that doe not know; and it muſt needes bee troubleſome alſo to thoſe that doe know how to place the ſame rightly, becauſe they muſt ſtand and apply a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant together with a needle to it every night when they would uſe it, unleſſe the ſame ſtand alwaies fixed abroad in its due poſition; and if it ſo doe, yet the unskilfull ſort cannot well tell how to make uſe of it, by reaſon (it conſiſting of two ſeverall parts or plates) of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21137:16"/> moveable part thereof, turning about within the outmoſt plate, and upon which the houre-lines are drawne, whoſe Index, (or long tooth, as he termeth it) being faſtned at the houre of 12. muſt be turned to the day of the Moone noted on the outermoſt or fixed part, and to the houre of the change (as he ſaith) accounting from 12. of the clocke; in which he hath not ſufficiently expreſſed the meaning thereof, for ſuch as are but meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly skilled in theſe things, to underſtand, and ſo (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) hath not well declared the making and uſe of the ſame. Vpon the outermoſt or fixed part, hee draweth a circle, which hee divideth into 30. parts for the thirty dayes of the Moone, after this manner: Now becauſe (ſaith he) the Moone finiſheth her courſe in 29. dayes, 12. houres, and 44. minutes, (that is, from the Sunne, being in a meane conjunction with him, till ſhe be with him againe by the like conjunction) part or divide the aforeſayd circle into 30. parts, ſo as 29. of them being equall, the thirtieth or laſt muſt not be ſo great as one of the other parts by ⅓, that is, it muſt containe ⅔ of one of them; by which account (if it were true) the Moone ſhould finiſh her ſayd courſe in 29. dayes, and 16. houres, (which make ⅔ of the naturall day) whereas the ſame is but 29. dayes, and 12. houres, or ½ of the day naturall, and about ¾ of an houre over, and therefore it doth not conſequently follow, that the laſt part ſhould containe ⅔ of one of the reſt, but rather ½ onely: Indeed (for mine owne part) I muſt confeſſe, I never made tryall of this Dyall, and therefore can ſay the leſſe of it, neither doe I know whether the ſame were of his owne deviſing or not; But ſure I am that this our Horizontall Dyall is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way as exact as that, and ſerveth to a more generall uſe, it being of uſe and delight for all ſorts of men, and more eſpecially <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch as know not how to finde the houre of the night artificially by other wayes: for if they can but know how to get the true age of the Moone (which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21137:16"/> is eaſily done by an Almanacke, as I ſayd before) they may as eaſily obtaine the time of the night by this Dyall (or the like made upon any other Plane, when the Moone ſhineth thereupon; and that ſufficiently enough) as the time of the day by any Sunne-dyall when the Sunne ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on the ſame: But if any liſt to make uſe of ſuch a kind of Dyall, as that of Mr. <hi>Fales,</hi> lately mentioned, they may uſe another way to finde the time of the night more exactly thereby: For the houre-lines being drawne upon the moveable or turning plate or wheele (as before is ſayd) which ſhould now be ſo large as each houre may be diſtinctly divided into ſuch a number of parts, as that you may gueſſe at any one minute thereupon, (which may conveniently 15. or 20. parts, for then each part will containe but foure or three prime minutes of time) If they can have a Table of the Moones comming to their Meridian artificially and exactly calculated for every day in the yeare, and ſo for every yeare ſeverally (which in ſome yeares is to be found in one Almanacke or other, if truſt may be given to them) then to make uſe of this Dyall in any night of the yeare when the Moone ſhineth, they muſt looke out that day in the ſayd Table, and right againſt it, under its proper moneth is ſet the houre and minute of the Moones comming unto the Meridian for that day and place: then the Dyall being rightly placed if they bring that houre and minute noted on the inward or moveable part to the Meridian line noted on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt or immoveable part, and ſo let the houre-lines in that poſition, the ſhadow of the ſtile ſhall ſhew the houres of that night exactly, without having any regard to the dayes of the Moones age, noted upon the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part, as in the former, and therefore this muſt needes be a ſurer way than the former, for that depending upon the houre or indeed the houre and minute of the Moones change (in which the Almanackes doe ſo much differ) muſt needes cauſe an errour in the obſervation of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21137:17"/> time: and neither this way nor the former, can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed upon any Plane beſides the Equinoctiall, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of the inequality of angles in all other Planes, whoſe houre-lines make angles of interſection.</p>
            <p>And now in the concluſion of this worke, thus much I ſay; that if the beſt inventions and conceits of men be haunted by ſome Momaicall Spirit at one time or other, as it is certaine they alwayes have beene and ſtill are: Then ſure I am, and I muſt not otherwiſe expect but that this of mine (being ſo meane in compariſon of many that have beene ſo haunted) will be in the ſame caſe; yet I may care the leſſe, becauſe the beſt of all have beene ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>Momus</hi> his cenſures: But whoſoever hee be, that ſhall carpe hereat, or evilly cenſure it; if he can finde out any other more exact way for this kinde of Horologio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie than that which I have conceited and here deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered (it having not beene done before by any, for ought that I doe know or could ever heare) as I doubt he cannot for the reaſons formerly alleadged; my requeſt to him is, that he would be pleaſed to beſtow a little paines in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the ſame into light, and then I deſire, that for ever after, this may (as deſervedly it might) lye hidden in oblivion and dakeneſſe: In the meane ſeaſon I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe my poore endeavours to the courteous and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable acceptation of the friendly Reader and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, ſaying to him, (concerning this matter) ſomewhat in effect as I ſayd before,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Vive, vale, ſi quid noviſtirectius iſt is,</l>
               <l>Extrahito in lucem; ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21137:17"/>
            <head>AN ADDITION CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KING AND VSE OF SEVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall plaine Scales, for the exact and moſt ſpeedy menſuration of Circles, Spheres, and Cylinders, and for Gauging of Veſſels.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, a Scale for the taking of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of any Circle, and thereby to finde the ſuperficiall content in foote meaſure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond, a Scale for the taking of the Axis or diameter of any Sphere or Bullet, and thereby to finde out the ſolide content in inch meaſure: and if I had the true proportions of metals, I could have fitted a Scale for every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall metall, ſo that the Axis of any Sphere or Bullet, being taken by his proper Scale and cubed, the cube ſhould be the weight of the Bullet or Sphere propoſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third, a Scale or line for the finding of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21137:18"/> the ſolid content of any Cylinder in foote mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and that as ſpeedily as of any Paralellepipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by two multiplications onely.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth a line or ſcale for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giving of the ſolid content of any Cylinder in wine gallons.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth for the ſame in Ale Gallons, and theſe by two multiplications onely.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The length of each Scale ſeverally as followeth.</head>
                  <p>1. Firſt, the length of the Scale for taking of the diameter of a Circle is 1. 1283. foote, that is, one foote and 1283. parts of a foote divided into 10000. parts: This ſcale or line, and likewiſe all the reſt, muſt be firſt divided into ten equall parts and each of thoſe parts ſubdivided into ten equall parts (after the uſuall manner) and ſo the whole line or ſcale will containe 100. equall parts; or you may conceive each of thoſe laſt ten parts to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided alſo into ten other parts, and then the whole line is ſuppoſed to containe 1000. equall parts; but indeed 100. parts will be ſufficient: Then know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the length of every line or ſcale, you may take that in your Compaſſes, &amp; turne it over upon a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, as many times as you ſhall thinke to be fitting.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>The length of the</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>2. <hi>For the Axis of a Sphere,</hi> 1. 2405. inch.</item>
                           <item>3. <hi>For Cylinders.</hi> 1. 0838. foot.</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>For Wine meaſure.</hi> 6. 65. inches.</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>For Ale meaſure.</hi> 7. 02. inches.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The uſe of theſe ſeverall Scales briefely in their order.</head>
                  <p>By the firſt Scale or line, having taken the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21137:18"/> of any Circle propoſed (whethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r in Pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Seeling, or the like) if you ſquare that dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter (the whole line repreſenting but one foote) the ſame ſhall be the ſuperficiall content of the circle in foote meaſure, as nearely as can be found by any other way whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>So if the diameter taken, be 4. 25. of the ſcale, the ſupernaturall content of the Circle will be 18. 0625. foote. The like may be done for inch meaſure.</p>
                  <p>2. By the ſecond ſcale, having taken the Axis or diameter of any Sphere or Bullet propoſed: if you cube that Axis; the ſame cube ſhal be the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid content of the Sphere or Bullet in inch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
                  <p>So the Axis of a Sphere being 8. 50. of his ſcale; the ſolid content will be found to be 614. 125000. cubicall inches: the like may be made for foote meaſure.</p>
                  <p>3. By the 3. 4. and 5. ſcales; if the diameters and length be taken by their proper ſcales, and the ſquare of the diameter be multiplyed in the length, the product thereof ſhall be the ſolid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in foote meaſure, Wine gallons or Ale gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, according to the qualitie of the ſcale and meaſure.</p>
                  <p>So if the length of a Cylinder be 12. 00. by the third ſcale, and the diameter 1. 75. the ſolide content thereof will be found to be 16. 7500. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique feete: the like for inch meaſure.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21137:19"/>
               <head>Rules for Gauging of Veſſels.</head>
               <p>It is generally holden (and I my ſelfe have found by ſeverall trialls) that a wine Gallon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth 231. cubicall inches, or very neare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; and that an Ale Gallon conteineth 272¼ cubicall inches in liquour.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The 1. Rule.</head>
                  <p>This rule is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſt and certaineſt of all other, and the way to prove other rules by, becauſe it is grounded upon good demonſtration, but withall it is ſomewhat tedious: See Mr. <hi>Oughtreds</hi> booke of the Circles of proportion.</p>
                  <p>The Rule is thus.</p>
                  <p>Adde the ⅓ of the Circle at the head, to ⅔ of the Circle at the bongue in inches; the ſumme of this addition being multiplyed by the length in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, giveth the ſolide content in cubique inches, which being divided by 231 (if wine meaſure) or 272¼. (if Ale meaſure) the quotient is the content in Gallons.</p>
                  <p>The readieſt way for the finding of the ⅓ and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the ſuperficiall contents of circles at the head and bongue, is this.</p>
                  <p>1. As 1. is to 0.5237.</p>
                  <p>So is the ſquare of the diameter at the bongue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ⅔ of the circle at the bongue.</p>
                  <p>2. As 1. is to 0.2619.</p>
                  <p>So is the ſquare of the diameter at the head, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the circle at the head.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21137:19"/>
                  <p>Theſe ⅔ and ⅓ added together, make<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meane Circle, whoſe diameter may (not unfitly) be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a meane diameter: and thus much for the firſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The 2. Rule.</head>
                  <p>1. <hi>How to finde the meane or equated diameter which is thus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Multiply the difference of the Diameters by 7, and adde the product to the diameter at the head; the ſumme thereof is the equated diameter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>To finde the Content of any Veſſell in Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt finde the equate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diamete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, and ſquare it; Then firſt by inch meaſure.</p>
                  <p>As 294. (if Wine meaſure) or 346. 5. (if Ale meaſure) are to the length in inches: So is the ſquare of the equated diameter, to the content in Gallons.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21137:20"/>
                  <p>The reaſon of theſe two numbers, is the ſame with that of a Circle to its circumſcribing ſquare, that is, as 11. to 14. wherefore, if the cubique inches contained in a Gallon be augmented by 14. and the product divided by 11. the quotient will yeeld a number, which ſhall be the Diviſor. Now for the triall of this rule: Suppoſe a veſſell to be in length. 39. 9. inches, the head, bongue and equated diameter as before; the ſquare of the equated diameter is 1105. 9. which multiplyed in the length, giveth 44125. 41. cubique inches, which divided by 294. (if Wine meaſure) giveth in the quotient 150. 08. Gallons of Wine: but by the ſcale enſuing, the ſayd veſſell would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine but 149⅓. So is the difference about ⅔ of a Gallon, which being ſo ſmall, is not to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Art of gauging.</p>
                  <figure/>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21137:21"/>
                  <head>The uſe of this Gauging Ruler is thus.</head>
                  <p>Firſt finde the equated diameter, as before. Then multiply the ſquare of the equated diameter by the length of the veſſell; the product is the content in wine Gallons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another Example.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21137:21"/>
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Equated diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Or I might here take 26, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the fraction approacheth nigh unto an unitie: for in this kinde of mixt numbers, when the laſt figure of the fraction towards the left hand exceedeth the number of 5. there (to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd the fraction) you may adde an unitie to the whole part thereof, and ſo make it an abſolute number, and when it wants of 5. (as in the laſt fraction) you may (if you pleaſe) reject the fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which will breed no ſenſible errour in the worke) and retaine the whole number onely, or you may cut off all the figures (if there be many) ſaving the laſt two or three towards the left hand, and ſo make it onely a centeſimall or milleſimall fraction: So the fraction of the laſt number afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, may be onely. 24, which here ſignifieth very neare ¼ of a Gallon.</p>
                  <p>The queſtion in this laſt example, is as difficult as moſt that you ſhall meete with of this kind, and therefore if this be rightly underſtood, all other queſtions of the ſame nature may be eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
                  <p>Here I might have ſhewed the uſe of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcales for this purpoſe, and likewiſe the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of taking the diameters of veſſels at the head and bongne by this Ruler, but that this is a thing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21137:22"/> not unknowne to ſuch as are exerciſed in gauging of Veſſels, the ſame being fully ſhewed in bookes of gauging already publiſhed and therefore mine intention was not, here to ſet downe the whole Art of gauging, but briefely to ſhew the making and uſe of this gauging Ruler, which was never publiſhed before, although I could have ſet forth the ſame long before this time; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any ſhall thinke good to make tryall of this or any of the reſt which I have here delivered, let them ſpeake of them according to what they ſhall finde in them, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="editors_note">
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe two ſeverall workes</hi> (friendly Reader) <hi>contained in this booke and ſo preſented to thy view, being (each of them) but of a ſmall quantity, and alſo as novelties, we have therefore thought it meete and commodious thus to connect them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21137:22"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 3. read, but at contrary. p. 5. l. 2. r. poſitions. l. 28. r. Meridian. p. 16. l. 29. read this his dyall. p. 17. l. 14. r. conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently be 15. or 20. l. 28. for let r. ſet. p. 21. l. 8. for ſupernaturall r. ſuperficiall. l. 21. r. lengths.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
